simon rex untrue those are some places
you can find more about may I will be
posting these slides later I'll give you
a link at the end we can get all the
demo code things I'll be showing you
going fairly quickly through some
examples so I've been working with CSS
and CSS really became a thing since it
first appeared in browsers I've been
doing this for that long and with that
kind of history
CSS today is absolutely amazing we can
do a whole heap of stuff that put off a
long time we could only do with
Javascript or by you know using a whole
stock of sliced up images but CSS layout
seem to get itself stuck somewhere in
about 2006 and essentially we're using
CSS for layout at the moment that was
never designed to be used for complex
full-page application layout and that
show of hands who here is generally
using some kind of framework bootstrap
Foundation also on four grades to the
layout exactly and so we view so awesome
the weapon we see this and I know it's
possible to not do this by using Sasha
whatever but if you view so a bootstrap
sites you will see this in the Moscow
and what we're doing here is we are
describing layout in moscow and whether
you care you don't care about semantics
last names
this is conceptually very heavy and it
makes it hard to do things like new
break points you know for small the
small viewport so whatever tropical
treats quite difficult for doing this in
a moscow who were doing this because
layout is hard and it is fragile and we
have business goals to meet you can't
just spent all day playing about with
CSS show ID system layout message they
are costing us and they're costing us
develop ours as we're all learning how
to do this stuff the coming at a cost of
an average or dog documents in fully
semantic way so so just still matters an
awful lot and they come at a cost of is
leaning on framework to deal with
complexity
and math rising market to our documents
were leaning on three processors and and
to abstract away these problems but
there is hope that it comes in the form
of a group of modules that are going to
redefine how we do lay out on the web
and these awful Xbox CSS grid layout and
the box alignment module these all our
new system for doing layout on the web
when we talk about these new modules we
tend to talk in terms of how they solve
our problems and the reason that they
solve these problems is that they shed
some characteristics that characteristic
solve existing last message do not have
they probably separate document so so it
and be sure to spray they give us true
alignment control they give us the
ability to send two things home has done
to me and they were sponsored by default
they remove the need to calculate
percentages to make columnist and most
importantly they give relationship to
each other in the context of an oval
layout and this is really important
because a lot of the problems we have
with our existing layout message is
because items in the layout do not
understand that the other items in the
layout exist if I float two blocks left
and right and the left one is shorter
than the right 1 I've got no way to tell
the left on block that it should
visually extend to the height of the
right how long she doesn't know it's
that didn't know how to lattice we've
been trying to create full height
columns for years maybe some people who
might remember the photo columns
technique using a vertically tiled
background image to create the illusion
version of a full-height column and
these are the techniques of a kind of
stock in trade for the web developer and
have been for years and they really
started to fall apart when responsive
came along this relationship is why
people jumped on the idea of display
table returned elements into a CSS table
and that gave them relationship because
table of elements not able to have a
relationship to each other and that's
why that kind of work to do things like
full height columns so flexible auction
good take this idea of relationship and
they really run with it and that's where
a lot of that power those full height
columns that's pretty much the basic
behavior flex function grid so you got a
simple text books example here we're
taking advantage of the initial default
values of the Flex proper change our
sidebar on our content of in side
effects contained on the Site baldwin's
to the height of the content the
background color goes all the way to the
bottom it doesn't help put behind the
text I can do the same with could dry
out just got a great on my rough element
composition in my sidebar my content
using line based positioning should all
of these examples idea of things
understanding that place in a wider
layout that's really important as long
as we've talked about separation of
content from the display content market
from the way it looks that was kind of
the rallying cry of the CSS layout
movement you trying to persuade our
table using friends that they should
start using this new shiny CSS layout
relevant tables but it's been something
of a failed promise we can you have the
ideal source told one display but once
you start dealing with responsive will
try to have multiple displays of that
content it's very difficult to not stop
messing about with the sole soda in
order to get the different kinds of this
place that we want to take a look at
flex Fox got my navigation here it's
very simply laid out with the Xbox I'm
using space between
Joe flex folks are signing the space
left over after displaying items by
fresh direction property is set to row
and that's the initial behavior for Xbox
you can also use color just play the
iTunes a column if I want to switch the
order reflects heightened I can set the
Flex direction property to reverse or we
could use column of you can also set the
order using the order property so I've
got a bunch of items displaying in short
order in effect container given the
model number so you can see that tomoda
we can change the order to now the
number 13 visually
gives us the power to change the order
of elements in not one but two
dimensions
a parent element assets display great
and I'm setting up a three column grid
positioning these items using but Colin
grid row property's value before the
photo / is the content content starts on
the value after as the land line and
that let's just do something like this
positioning items around the grid both
in columns and rows the constraint is
the grid items like sex I need to be a
direct route of the element that's
become a quick container but the small
so in addition to this placing of items
on an explicit grid grid layout also
includes auto placement rules they let
us take a chunk of content to upgrade
and the grid will just display for us to
the previous example if I remove all
positioning information grid these items
will be displayed by could ensure each
in a grid so if I add some more images
and some of those images a landscape and
portrait so out of class to any Li
elements that contain landscape images
and I can then set the grid column and
property to spend two lines so that
means my landscape images now spanned
two great tracks and my portrait once
found the default one track and so I get
this show in times of registered office
to iTunes report right now we've got one
that takes two trucks and then we've got
a gap because the next image is also
landscape it needs to track so by
default grid is progressing forward it's
keeping the items in Oranje unless I add
a property of grid auto flow with a
value of dense grid will fill the gas it
moves to the content it finds an image
that will fit a got a toll but he left
it will pick it up and it will pop it
into the space so you can see the item
for now become comes before Lightroom 3
in the visual display this is incredibly
powerful and also slightly scary so with
this power comes great responsibility
these new methods give us the ability to
separate document Jordan display in ways
we have never been able to do before and
we need to start having conversations
about how we do this in an accessible
way because ideally they should make
able to create really great source
documents and then get visual displays
that work well for different devices but
people may just say why don't you worry
about social anymore this will work
whatever I do I can just drag things
around the great that would be bad even
wish because items only become good
items Affleck sites and if they are
diabetic child of the container I think
there is a real danger that individuals
writing web pages offering tools or
people making JavaScript frameworks will
start to strip Moscow in order to make
it easy and have a flattish or so it is
easier to use these techniques I think
that's a real danger I think it's
something that we should be thinking
about as a community of these new
message coming to being this is from the
comment text box editor's draft
explained that order does not change the
logical order of the document it just
for the visual display so it appears
that the hardest challenge in web design
is vertical alignment and this is
something that new layout message so
this is the safest box alignment module
it's a module that contains the features
of CSS that relate to alignment and it's
basically reflects boxes the alignment
capabilities effects box brought out
they could apply to other layout message
so this is the vertical centering module
although it covers all the things to
like distribution of space overflows
logical positioning
disputes alignment we show one of the
key word values and the simple text
books example in Flex luxurious justify
content and online content to a line
items against one of the two exchanged
I've got navigation in a row and I use
justify content space between to line up
my first and last items flush with the
sides of the container and distribute
the rest of the space equally I can you
space around an equal amount of space is
then placed left and right of the items
there's a kind of half size space on
each end by setting a lion or justify
items on the facts contained and we're
changing the Alliance shelf and justify
self properties of each of the
individual items inside as you've
already seen
items in effect contain have
relationship by default the value of a
line items will be stretch which means
that item stretching across access and
all the same height despite not
containing content of the same height my
first navigation point that has got a
bit of text in via the things you'll
know to go to the same height as that
and other problems 2011 of CSS is doing
vertical centering a line item to send
the item sold center against the main
axis direction to call on the line item
sent to ascend to the items I was just
online stuff from using individual flex
items to change that line and properties
stretch of them center to get individual
items so this works with Flex folks you
can stop playing around with this you
know you can be using this data and
ultimately it's going to apply to all
kinds of layout and so this is
implemented in the grid specs so we can
have a look at how that's working in
grid upgrades degrade and I'm setting a
line items on the grid to center we've
got a repeating pattern of great
traction and then positioning my items
each grade OE astounding four lines
horizontally and vertically so each of
the full grid via Scopus four squares of
the background image might go see that
was also linked by default the item
without you stretch and fill the hole
because your cell line item to send the
items within the hour we can justify the
items saying good same placement but
this time we get this kind of alignment
I'm just like with the Xbox you got the
Alliance shell and justify sell
properties and that let you target
individual items and she could really
see how these properties work here
box as shown on the detailed stretch to
cover the gray area is set to launch
shelf and seat recline shop start and
day to align self center so we've got
these powerful alignment capabilities
and we can start using a legend for Xbox
the coming to other layout message
ultimately they may well apply to block
layout message will probably have the
ability to do things on the web for the
first time and being able to align
groups and individual items is really
vital for responsive design but we don't
know maybe how wide that viewport I
swear a lot of all had that kind of work
you know things like the the pho columns
idea is where they started to fall down
once I didn't know how wide that column
was going to be and that's the thing
with these new methods they are
essentially responsive by default
I'm sure everyone here knows that
there's a back in 2009 the Eastern
Market detailed and has a list of part
of this technique for creating fluid
bridge he was working with relative
phone sizes and note of the grid should
be treated in the same way that we could
divide the target with development by
the whip the context to give us a
percentage to use in place of absolute
sizes four columns in design I'm so it
came to pass that we all started
calculating these unlikely looking
numbers and sticking them in all the new
layout message was to retire a lot of
those calculations because they can't
just do this stuff for us we've already
seen how the most simple of Xbox
examples takes initiative iTunes
declared display flex on them and you
justify content with the value of space
between that value flexes with the
available space space as needed but
there's more than that because the Xbox
allows us to portion utley distribute
space between our item
now the Flex property is a shorthand for
three properties we've got flex grow
lecturing and flex basis
text books draft spectra gesture use the
shorthand for these properties because
they will reset the other values to
things that make sense and good company
says there's quite a lot of confusion
around these things were so here I am
setting flex flex shrink to one and that
means that every box every flex item can
grow and shrink to fit into the space
but the ideal box wit my Flex basis is
200 pictures and share this code applied
to some items will give me three boxes
of equal with the items to wrap we can
drug to induce mollen see that when the
boxes get smaller than 200 pixels a box
will wrap onto line to try and maintain
that 200 pixel basis to the final box
here is taking up all of the Station
Road too because the linemen just worked
out on a row by row basic if the vote he
has sworn I it's allowed to grow it will
grow it will fill the available space if
I don't want the boxes to grow i sat
next row 20 a wide window size my boxers
will just stay at the 200 picture if you
let the boxes wrapped the third item
will still drop down but it won't grow
and fill the line and you can talk
individual items to to hear about it
rules for box 300 boxes can grow and
shrink to two pixels but box three
cannot grow so you see what happens once
the boxes have to stretch wide than 200
pictures it stays 200 pixels the space
that's remaining is distributed between
the boxes that have allowed to grow but
there's more than this because
responsive design is about proportions
that's what all option to just about to
in order that we can maintain
proportions elements luxury can assign
different bodies just text grow on
fracturing
I'm setting box 32 flex groped
with my other two boxes that default
reflects Wang
this doesn't mean is that box three
becomes twice the size of the boxes it
means that after the 200 pixel basis has
been taken away from the available
within the container the rest of the
space is assigned to each item across
according to that flex growth factor
that sounds very confusing a good way to
figure it all out
is this play xbox test a tool you can
stick in a load of values and it will
tell you what you would come out with I
want to start playing around with it to
make century and once you understand
that you've got a head start to
understand FL unit this is a fraction
unit and like flex grow it allows you to
assign a fraction of the available space
so that take a quick look at this is my
simple grid it defines three columns or
with one out of the way so that creates
three equal which color if I change my
definition and create 600 pixels with
columns and absolute side column and
then 21 fraction unit callers great
first gives the fixed width 600 pixels
the remaining space it divides into two
and it gives off its one column to the
other if I change my last column 3 fo
the remaining space be divided 243 part
is given to the 301 Park into the water
this just light for Xbox means that we
can create fully flexible layout that
have so much fixed element in this is
just like the Holy Grail layout that we
used to try and build this was six
sidebars the liquid center weather
center column could be first in the show
order but would flex according to screen
with their like this should not seen
this in taxable this is the CSS grid
layout Ascot layout template us that CSS
gives you a layout on the center column
is set to one fraction unit that will
stretch on take up all of the
available which it will look something
like this which is a good 2005 era
layout it's not what wall aiming to
build these days but I feel that given
the history it's nice to know that we
can finally do it so it's a new system
for layout I think it raises a huge
amount of different possibilities I'm
very excited to see what happens it gets
into the hands of people who are
creative with their stuff well some
people like me who can just build things
we've got great we've got the Xbox and
then that's tied together with the
alignment of space distribution
properties from Fox alignment the key
difference between these two specs
people often say oh well which should I
be using should I use an ideal world
wanted got them both would I be using
Flex boxer would I use trade show for
Xbox is for one dimensional layout thats
things that can be laid out in a row or
laid out in a column although it was
essentially still got an unbroken line
which is for two-dimensional layout so
you working with was calling the
simplest example of this if we're at of
items using Flex books I've got a flex
basis here of 200 pixels and the items
are allowed to grow and shrink I have
got five items what happens here the
Flex items rap show each row start
acting like a new facts contained I'm
space distribution happens across the
row that's how it works
show at the top line we've got three
items and then we go to the next line
we've only got two items that allowed to
grow so it's different and they spread
out across there and then people say oh
well actually what I'd like to be able
to do is line up those two bottom iTunes
underneath the items at the top and
fresh box doesn't do this because it's
dealing with issues of unbroken line
which is where you want grid layout if
you want to do something like this
because she wanted to control both rows
and columns
with grid layout you do something like
this you wouldn't do anything with the
item is it all be controlled when you're
creating the grid and then the items
would be flown in flowed into it and
that would give you this kind of layout
so unless you actually especially said
something I want you to span across to
the column tracks you get them in single
trucks so this wonderful new goodness
reflects folks house that she got really
great for our sport at this point if you
can use your browser's you can use your
Xbox even if you have to sport old
browsers it's very possible to use quite
a lot of flex box has essentially an
enhancement to your layout soyuz older
methods and then be tweaked the
alignment and get things look pretty
tight using the Xbox but really everyone
should probably starting to use some
degree reflects box in their work at
this point because its bid got really
good support it's worth doing so proud
to offer grid layout not so good the
only browser that has any implementation
which is sort of live is I 1011 edge and
that is because the suspect came from
Microsoft they crashed early
implementation of it in those brushes
but it is quite different now to the the
current specification sheet was
essentially the very first
implementation of the spec for the best
stuff to work with is in chrome and
regular chrome but it's behind a
flagship need to enable the experimental
web platform features flag and then lots
of demos all things stuck shoney's today
you can have a look at them play about
with that would in blink show it should
chrome and opera is being done by
earlier sponsored by Bloomberg they're
also doing the work in WebKit WebKit
nightlies how quickly that enables you
need to use a WebKit prefix grades on
the edge backlog at high priority so I'm
assuming that intending to bring the
implementation up to the same spec
nothing else and Mozilla are currently
implementing great in Firefox quite a
lot of these examples work in Firefox
tonight
please adjust to a party fell out there
so great is coming and unlike flex books
which kind of trickled out it kind of
heartbroken states and changed and goes
already confused which has been
developed behind flags so when it does
eventually shift and browses it should
be fairly equal across browsers and very
complete and it's been kind of kept
behind the flag so that we don't have
this problem of it emerging in this
which is good news for when it does
arrive we can start using it with some
confidence it we've gotten your problem
just use it with I have lots and lots of
great examples to play with if you want
to go and have a look good by
example.com is why I keep all of my good
examples I can't put new ones up and I'd
love to have more people looking at this
stuff in particular who got an interest
in accessibility it's not my of
expertise not to love to see more
conversations happening around you know
using these new last message and
accessibility think it's a very very
important subject I have got a office
hours thing at lunch so very happy to
have a chat about any of this stuff and
you will find my slides all the code
examples of that year and you can always
treated me on Twitter or drop me a line
of talking about this stuff thank you
very much for listening